It turns out that consistency does
matter and here's how. Let's say that in
program order two cores do this. The
first core is going to store a one into
location D and then store a one into
location F. Let's say that D and F are
both zero initially. The second core
loads F into R1 and then loads D into
R2. And let's say that now we print the
registers R1 and R2. Note that we can
have an out of order processor that
reorders loads and stores.
So in execution order, core one might
still be doing the stores in the same
order, but core two decides to reorder
these two loads. Note that in a
uniprocessor reordering of loads,
if this core is not writing to these
locations, is perfectly okay. And in
fact, even in a multiprocessor, most of
the time it's okay. Now let's look at
what's possible to get in R1 and R2
after this. In program order, these two
loads on core two might execute before
these two stores in core one. So we can
get R1 and R2 are zero. Here, these two
loads
in core two, although they've been
reordered, can still happen before core
one gets to store.
So we can get the same thing. These two
loads can happen after the two stores.
So we can get one in both registers
here. In execution order, even if we
reorder them, they can execute after the
stores, so we can get one in both of
them. In the program order, if these two
happen like this, in between the two
stores, we can get R1 when we load is
still loading the zero here, but R2
when we load is already loading the one.
The same thing can happen here. If these
two loads are in between the stores,
then R1 is going to be zero because it
comes before this.
And R2 is going to be one because it
happens here. And now it gets
interesting. We have seen that there are
these three possibilities. So, the
question is, but can we get R1 to be one
while R2 is zero? And in the program
order, if we consider that, it's not
possible. R1 being one means that when
we read F, we read one.
That means that this load has to come
after this store. If that happens,
then this load has to be after this
load, too.
So, pretty much if we executed this
here,
then this has to be here.
And that means that if we read one from
F, we will read one from D, as well. So,
the R1 = 1, R2 = 0 cannot happen in
program order. But here, R1 = 1 means
that this load needs to be here. And we
can get a zero in R2 if this load comes
here. So, if we put the stores in
between the loads
in the execution order like this, we
will get a situation that was not
possible in the original program order.
So, the programmer might have expected
that this code can never result in this,
but in an out-of-order processor
execution on each core, it can. And note
that this doesn't violate coherence at
all. In all cases, a load and a store
obeyed coherence. But do we really care
about that? Sure, for some obscure
orderings, this can happen. Do we really
care? When does it really matter that
this doesn't happen and it does?